[Music]
Carl H Smith pollutant
I like the H for the differentiation me
too because I presume that it's probably
quite a few Carl Smith's out there there
is too many yeah there was a lot of Tim
Hortons as well but I changed my name
and now I'm the only one very clever
there are father issues wrapped up in
that obviously and that's not something
I would have planned on saying if we
weren't in the current state we are now
but I'm very interested to sit down and
talk to you and we are here to discuss
engineering humanity and altered states
of consciousness mm-hmm
which is a very complicated and complex
thing to even God feel yourself into as
a as a topic and we have to be careful
talking about some of this stuff because
it's not precisely clear what humanity
is it's not precisely clear what we are
but perhaps you could introduce yourself
first of all to our audience and tell us
a little bit about your background and
your interests okay so yeah I'm I'm
based in London and I run a research
center there at Raven Symone University
London and the research centre is
looking at how we use technology to
learn is the very broad as technology in
hearts learning is the field but when
you actually look at how unsuccessful
technology is in making us learn then
you start to look at why and what you
know what what all the sort of other
aspects of of us as humans that make us
so easily distracted so easily addicted
so easily you know sidetracked from
cognition and how much of that can be
fixed and it's a bit like with the whole
mental health question so if you're not
well mentally then you're not going to
learn you know and we had a whole debate
last night about creativity and
suffering and actually is suffering
needed for creativity you know you with
a lot of bands their first albums the
best then as soon as they're successful
they sort of like take their foot off
the off the accelerator and then they
become a bit sort of you know and a lot
of artists actually become sort of very
much like
as they get towards their latent latter
years not many people keep up the
innovation so yes that is this the human
condition that I'm really interested in
and how technology can help with that
and one of the things you said we don't
know what Humanity is which is true and
actually humanity's normally defined by
what it isn't
and we you know we we come up with all
these ideas of you know that we're that
we're not this and we're not that and
we're superior to all the other species
whereas actually I think we need to
address that and actually to be a lot
more humble and you know we've talked a
lot about transhumanism and all these
things that saying that we're going to
evolve as humans where it's actually you
could argue we're going backwards a lot
of the time and by wiping out and create
you know causing such havoc in in the
natural world you know we need to really
question what what what we are and what
consciousness is because if we're going
to try and put consciousness into into
machines and yet we don't really know
what it is then what are we doing right
absolutely and in particular if we want
to capture what their human is in
consciousness then that adds another
little bit of spice to the whole
procedure but I'm I'm interested in I
suppose talking personally a bit here
what are some of the experiences in your
life that have been most sort of
iconically related to the story you find
yourself living now like what is it that
you find yourself searching for in in
what it is to be human or what is it
there that has to be preserved what
makes you want to preserve that like
what are you searching for that kind of
way of thinking if you know what I'm
looking mmm
yeah I suppose I'm really interested in
the the multiple self you know and
exploring that I suppose I've become
aware that the the cult of the
individual is causing a lot of the
trouble that we're we're experiencing
and a lot of my most powerful
experiences have been non-dual hmm so I
mean you know you simply I am both of us
and so are you
and having those sorts of experiences
wrap it radically change your behavior
because you stop thinking that you can
throw things away because there is no
way right you know it's it's all you and
everything is up for grabs you know
everything matters everything matters
everything matters so simple experiences
that you know happen spontaneously that
you can't explain like out-of-body
experiences life reviews you know these
sorts of experiences are I think if
everyone could have them like ever if
everyone could have reliable lucid dream
states we wouldn't be so caught up in
consumerism we wouldn't be so caught up
with buying the the latest car because
we would be so busy like driving fantasy
cars in our Detroit in our dreams hmm
hmm how far away do you think are we
from that that world where people don't
want to leave their rooms well I mean
that sort of that's already happening in
if you think about the hikikomori in
japan where they're already half a
million plus are living in in in
isolation you could argue a lot of us
are living in isolation even if we are
out in the world but I think that we can
we can explore these liminal spaces like
the dream world and you know if you can
if you can empower people by giving them
an out-of-body experience with
technology or giving them a reliable
Drita lucid dream state then maybe maybe
they become more isolated or maybe they
become more willing to see the world as
a canvas hmm so what came up for me
there is I still under the rubric of
feeling thinking seeing knowing somehow
that we are connected in really
fundamental ways mmm that still doesn't
precisely answer the question of how we
should be given that's the case mm-hmm
because it
also seems to be the case that were
caught in a cycle of becoming aware and
evermore of our connection to things but
then also returning to a kind of
cognition that's necessary for breaking
the world up doing practical things in
it it's not clear to me there could be
coherence as such or life as we know it
without that oppositional dynamic now
you might put in contrast to the kind of
unitary oneness consciousness which is
more like a pure apprehension and it's
not it's not precisely you can't talk
about it as pure like there's
differentiation in there or not it it's
very it's difficult to conceive of of
being without there being both the
non-dual state but then also the
transition to the to the dualistic which
then becomes a sort of a state of
multiplicity because of course there's
so many ways you can box up the world
and we're all different despite being
the same and it's also complicated so we
have to find somehow some way of
relating in that broad landscape where
we know in some sense we are somewhat of
the same kind but we all need unique
places in it like that the individuation
process is the kind of particular izing
out the fundamental conditions that are
pre given in a sense and they are
realized in myriad unique ways then
still have to sort of harmonize together
as a collective and so I wonder if
anything comes up for you there
definitely to do with how virtual
reality augmented reality could this be
some sort of solution do you think hmm
well I think we definitely want to move
on from journalism I think you dualism
has its place but if you think about you
know if we define ourselves with dualism
then we lead to more discrimination we
lead to more cul-de-sacs and I think
definitely don't want to be in a non
dual state all the time either but you
you want a stack you want to create like
a like a cookery book of different
states of consciousness where you can
reliably go into into them you can
master your consciousness rather than be
a slave to it and I think it is your
birthright
change your consciousness let you change
the channels on your television mm-hmm
and I think that's where we've gone
wrong that we change our channels we
just consume other people's content or
we just we don't we don't create content
for ourselves we don't change we don't
create new forms of consciousness for
ourselves and I think if you if you can
empower people to do that then you know
that's that's the new world right and I
and I guess a question might be sorry I
knew I didn't ask you a question about
the VR and AR stuff so yeah obviously
virtual reality is dangerous because it
could lead to more heat amore you know
the Japanese aren't even using VR really
at the moment it hasn't really taken off
as we expected it's still on its way on
in terms of a mass scale adoption but it
boxes you in you know is you know is it
is an isolation another art form of
isolation but it can be very empowering
if you use it for the right application
areas so for meditation for going inward
but I think augmented reality is a
fascinating area where we can be back in
the world and actually what's really
important is to be aware of all the
wonders in the world and to you know
that most people know all the logos or
the top-25 logos but they don't know
what the top-25 trees are you know they
so if you can help people by giving them
a layer of information over that over
the real world that will empower them to
to have interests in the world again to
to you know use something like Pokemon
go to get people out there to vote or to
get people out there to meet other
like-minded people I mean these things
are massive double-edged swords but for
one for one example you got mark Farid
who's gonna wear the oculus rift for a
month and look through somebody else you
know he's not gonna have access to his
own eyes or his own hearing for a month
and he's chosen a month because that's
how long it takes to form habits mm-hmm
so what he's testing is that whole
question of what is the personality
mm-hmm is the personality fluid anyway
and if you know you know a lot of people
go on for pastner's for ten days at a
time
there and a lot of people can't handle
it because suddenly without talking
without being able to look at any form
of media and you're just there with your
own thoughts and suddenly the thoughts
fall away and then you're like well what
actually is there mm-hmm one one
challenge with trying to figure that out
is getting clear on I don't think you
can get clear on it but what period of
time should be used to evaluate what
comes up you might have let's say a very
strange 20 minutes right or strange few
weeks but how you act in the world in
relationship to other people how you
relate to yourself later on over a long
period of time it seems to me this is
also relevant when understanding the
personality and its effect
mm-hmm but this kind of problem comes up
for me and lots of thinking at the
moment it's just not clear over over
what period of time which judgments are
relevant and part of my concern or one
area that I could see hasty conclusions
being drawn as to what's really real is
like one way to put it would be almost
like fetishes fetishizing the present
because in some profound sense that is
what's most real I mean that's the
moment we're sharing right now but if
you take the idea of the unconscious
seriously well then there's a whole
bunch of stuff that's unconscious hmm
right and that stuff is still playing
out to some degree you can still
construe those different parts of
yourself as having aims and being
involved in the world at different
levels and over different periods of
time and yeah you'd want to be very
clear let's say that certain things
we're not being repressed or or
what-have-you so yes it's very
challenging isn't it because you also
think of the human being as something
which develops over time
and there's plenty that has not yet come
out in the child that might one day come
out that has them be president or a
ruler or a magician or whatever it is
and and like an acorn becoming an oak
tree what is possible at the fullest
extent of actualization is is not clear
and there's a certain sense in which you
can only be in touch with that in the
most vague ways that you almost sort of
vibe off other people and I don't really
know what to make of all of that it's
just it's just thoughts as far as it
goes but you're right I mean I think the
present moment everyone says about let's
be present this most important thing to
be present but actually I get a lot out
of just jumping out of the present
moment and having this kind of double
consciousness where I'm able to because
I've written a diary for like 30 years
so I can you talk about the subconscious
and and how deep and how vast that is as
an area to play in and that's part of
what my diary is so I can like jump out
of the local view and jump into this
macroscopic view where I can see the
overview and get the overview effect and
you know with the astronauts that
suddenly saw the planet from that
perspective having a huge almost like a
non dual experience so I think once you
realise that there's lots to be gained
when you're not in the present moment
then that really gives you an impetus to
actually do the quantified self thing be
do track your your your behavior over
time because I like to see how creative
I've been over a month right you know
and that inspires me in that next moment
to do more to be creative and actually
when you write a diary it's almost like
a feedback loop so you get to the point
where you're I'm writing my diary in
order to live my life and not to repeat
myself so because I've I know what I've
written over 30 years I know what I
don't want to keep doing right and and
also you can take cross sections through
your life so you can look at this day
last year before new year before new
year before the year before and use that
in a way that you could never use your
real memory yeah so to use it as a
technology actually and I'm not you're
turning your life into architecture yeah
allows all of those phases of your life
to start communicating again right and
that's again a hugely powerful way of
actually I mean it's interesting because
people talk about that as a sort of
turning your life into a commodity or
whatever but I just think that we
already live for a thousand months and
actually people feel immortal so if you
if you actually do record stuff then
it's an incredible engine for for
learning and for innovation right I've
heard you talk about memory palaces mmm
before and I find that really
fascinating almost like a superpower
yeah I've heard people speak about they
go to places in their minds and I think
it was you who mentioned that this is
what some of the Greek orators with used
to memorise long speeches yeah could you
describe that what that is yeah sure so
I mean I my background was art history
then I did computer science and then I
did architecture for seven years and
when I was doing architecture I was 3d
modeling a lot and I noticed it changed
my brain you know it did something to me
doing all that 3d modeling and I'm still
trying to understand it but because I
was modeling very large ancient
buildings I suddenly had like I could
see further down the road when I was
driving so I had all these unintended
consequences and then I was then I
learned about memory palaces and memory
palaces very simply are this system of
holding information so the Greek artists
didn't write there seven our speeches
down they held them in virtual space in
their heads in architecture so they
would typically have an amphitheater and
that amphitheater will be filled with
their 7:00 hour speech and then they
would just walk through it in order to
trigger the whole seven out speech so
what did they have that we lost with the
technology of writing and literacy and
can we go back to something like that
with augmented reality because augmented
reality is putting information into
space again hmm so you know can we can
we you
have a superpower from adopting that
ancient methodology and applying it to
our modern tech mmm yeah it's very very
fascinating something else that came up
for me as well back on the theme we're
talking before about relating to the
present and then also getting that
oversight on it there's this I wonder if
there's any if that kind of maps onto a
distinction you can make between
meditation and contemplation mmm a kind
of retreating let's say from identifying
with particular thoughts or images that
come to mind and trying to allow things
to rise and let them pass sort of
identifying more with with the flow and
experience as such without getting too
caught up on any one given his fixation
of it and then converse of that which is
still done in a mindful way in some
sense is then the pudding and the first
part is kind of like breaking up the
frame the second part is kind of like
putting the frame back together and
getting this way of talking from an
excellent cognitive scientist called
John Vevey icky hmm who'll also be
having on the podcast soon actually and
I think that kind of distinction was
really helpful for me in trying to
understand the value of dropping in and
out of a certain it's the SEC almost
like the different parts of a flow state
to some degree you're trying to be
really present but then allowing insight
and and building out the right kind of
insight and grasping the world again
it's got breaking up and then remaking
it mmm and I think I don't know that it
came up for me is something going on
there and it's almost like something to
be striven for in conversation as well
and we're talking before in what this
would be like to do this and I'm
fascinated by what it is to cultivate
the right kind of relationship in
conversation mmm
so that you can properly attend without
grasping like what am I thinking I have
to say next what precisely am I trying
to do here to really listen and then to
get in the mode way you can identify
with the right things you know and then
build them out and look there's a lot
that has to go into it but there's
there's something I like about that
distinction there
yeah I mean I suppose I'm very
interested in the default mode Network
and the power of psychedelics to turn it
off temporarily and was to get into that
altered state where we're we were not
having that gnat brain chatter yes you
know and I think if we can maybe not
rely on psychedelics to do that but and
find other ways of doing it regularly
and I know there are many methods and
I'm really interested in creating like a
database of them and putting creating a
stack of all these different methods and
like just getting out there so that
people can can because what's really
interesting is that you can create a
stack of all these different ways of
doing just that but then each person
will react differently to each technique
mm-hmm so it's not just the the stack
you need to create it's also an
awareness that each culture is different
each gender is different each you know
it's um it's an absolute it's a it's a
huge minefield and that and ethically
obviously huge as well but I think that
it's the time to do it because that's
what I'm talking about the context
engineering it's about moving between
different contexts and learning from
them and building on them and and you
know moving away from a content based
economy to so actually looking at our
perception as the content and actually
changing the already existing content
content out there infinitely just by
changing the way we see it hmm very
interesting is this to do with moist
media what is what is moist media so
moist media is Rory a Scots term and
it's it's about looking at the
combination of dry wear with wet wear so
you know you've got technology being the
dry wear and the the biology being the
wet we're so you know psychedelics with
VR that's already you know a huge area
there's a there's a group on reddit
called rift in the mind where they're
doing lots of different VR experiences
with different psychedelics and
you know that that's a new science
really I mean you think about we don't
really understand VR on its own we don't
know we you know psychedelics are now
having a second Renaissance so we're
getting to understand a little bit more
but we're still scratching the surface
so we're already combining and that's
what I'm talking about with this cookery
book but I think that we we shouldn't
just because of the complexity we
shouldn't be scared we should actually
just be you know crowdsourcing
everything and getting you know getting
people to to contribute to this science
these new Sciences yeah well there's
certainly no shortage of explorative
types like you who are willing to do
that mmm does strike me that there's a
certain sort of individual who's more
cut out for it than another but you know
what also also came up for me there and
it gets to this difficulty in preparing
experiences for everyone because we do
have these differences and so in Stan
graphs research where he worked with or
studied thousands a couple thousand
patients I think in the 60s maybe 50s
maybe they began then it's pretty old
mm-hmm and in with psycho lytic therapy
with various doses of of LSD and what
the sort of map that he charts is one in
which for many people most of the time
to get to the transpersonal state some
of this stuff we're talking about
non-dual experiences or maybe ancestral
experiences or a temporal experiences or
out-of-body experiences that actually
there's a whole layer with lots of
layers of where you might understand
more it's just the individual
unconscious hmm various issues and
traumas and not just traumas but other
things complexes that have been
developed in the individual life growth
would argue since the birthing process
that have to be worked through in some
sense what you can get to get to these
other other places and it's like god
that's so that's so variable right
so to even engage in the kind of
unpacking or remembering it becomes such
an individual experience and you have to
be very careful of what's brought up
during that hmm you know we were talking
the other night actually about this the
trauma of birth mm-hmm
you know and how that sort of affects
you forever you know the your birth and
whether it was traumatic or it's always
traumatic right I mean but it's a
question of how traumatic and the first
two years of your life is so key to your
development and and I think yeah it's
this is I presume what makes us all so
individual that we that we have such
variations in these in fact in slightly
different ways yeah but I mean again
it's a tricky is that it's tricky to to
let that stop you you know and I think
that we need to we need to overcome our
our fear-based you know we're so locked
into fear and fear is the mind killer
you know and then all sorts of other you
know killers in every other level so I
think if we can empower people to you
know understand that it's all that it's
narratives it's all narratives that we
need to we need to stop telling
ourselves certain things and we need to
realize that worrying is a misuse of the
imagination hmm we need to start telling
ourselves the ones that are helpful
because we're not going to escape the
narrative no right so you know and I
think in part this is why figures like
Jordan Peterson and many others who have
become all of a sudden incredibly famous
public intellectuals they are
reconnecting many people with ancient
stories in ways that are more
comprehensible to let's say them a more
analytically minded group of people but
everyone archetypal stories are speaking
not only to the sort of effective
emotional side of us but also that we
can understand the
the benefits of narrative and its
function in ways that can be made
commensurate with some of the meaning
making processes in cognition that can
be understood from a more rational
scientific perspective so it's not clear
to me like what see I'm I'm hesitant to
when it comes to the topic of rewriting
narratives unless it's done in such a
way where one is connected with like an
appropriate life-giving narrative right
so if you've you're if you're oriented
towards some kind of positive
transformation in like I don't know the
right way to say this but I think there
has to be some kind of intention towards
betterment for yourself and others in
this connected way like I that that that
has to be part of this re-imagination of
what society can be because we know it's
going to change massively and it's not a
matter of burying our heads about it and
it's not a matter of letting fear and
worry stop necessary exploration but
it's still surely crucial to try and get
as close to the cusp as possible of what
memes are currently gripping us what in
them is vital what in them needs to be
changed I don't I don't think we can
escape that that like you kind of waking
like a philosophy as a kind of waking up
into who you are where who you are
becomes in some sense the recognition of
a different string that you weren't sure
was being pulled before but now it was
they're being pulled all along and and
maybe you can orient the process somehow
and and maybe in with this staff you
talk about going these other states of
consciousness you can get some kind of
apprehension of the whole somehow but
then all of a sudden we come back and
we're now now part of the you know just
a part again like I feel myself right
now
not that pleased with what I can bring
forward and given how some of this
night's gone with the change of venue
and everything like that it's it's this
switch up switch up between perspectives
and what you can bring to the table but
this nevertheless I don't know I'm
interested in what you can seek within
that flow and what can bring them all
together again and look it's all it's
all very confusing
mmm yeah I mean one thing I'd say is
that I'm really interested in perceptual
persistence you know like not not just
altered altered states but altered
traits you know and metaprogramming you
know it's like all the things that
you're describing all of this you know
noise if you like it's like how do we re
turn the volume down on our neuroses or
whatever it is you want to call it and
how do we how do we get into flow States
through good diet good sleep good just
basic but don't be obsessed with like
you know positive thinking or and I
think I think that we need to be more
positively and different we actually
need to be more Taoist we need to accept
all of the stuff that comes in and not
try and not try and like hide from the
bad times because they're you know we
know that happens right so it's
it's all about how you respond to it and
and that's that's again what context
engineering is about is like you know
it's a form of alchemy you're you're you
know you're it's you're very lucky to be
alive no matter what the circumstances
are and I think it's non-duality you
know the death stay is arguably you know
always around the corner we live for
such a short amount of time and I think
that we you know we're we're in this
this this local point of view but also
right in the Godhead right at the same
time right yes no I think I think that's
really beautifully put and it's
something about the process of relating
between these two states although of
course on in some sense the the you
being in the Godhead is
pure potential and so it's everything
not nothing because you can't conceive
it from the other state and then the
other state is all possible kinds of
actualization so it's not precisely two
states right it's more the
differentiation and flux of life that
somehow in process that that the process
of mediation we find ourselves sort of
we are on that train and you know and
there's ways I think to affirm being on
that train and there are ways to or
attitudes you can take rather of
affirmation and and I think in that mode
it's something like a loving affirmation
because it's a self i can't
conceptualize it as anything else other
than us at a self love which then
becomes love for everything mm-hmm
and then conversely and the the more the
more tragic alternative is to sort of
look at that as some sort of just
continual parody and but it's like not
love love affirmation for it I don't see
an alternative and it seems more real
somehow and something about experiences
processes practices individually
collectively that enable the recognition
of of this dynamic fascinating and
important and yeah it's really cool to
hear you you put it like that actually
because in so many ways that dual is and
that dynamic that is what's been a
motivating relationship to articulate
for me mm-hmm and I think it's one that
is part of the
current conversation an important sense
I want to talk to you for a lot longer
but I we both just heard the footsteps
of the manager of this venue outside we
didn't talk about DMT we didn't talk
about so many things but I think we are
going to talk about a lot more in the
future so Carl mate
thank you
[Music]